A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Politics - New York City Office, Series J.1 FA345
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Politics - New York City Office, Series J.1
1935-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
United States. International Development Advisory Board
Rockefeller family
Inter-American Development Commission
Ruebhausen, Oscar M.
Rockefeller, Mary (Mary Todhunter Clark)
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Whitman, Ann
Morrow, Hugh
United States. Office of Inter-American Affairs
Hinman, George
United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services
United States. Dept. of State
United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs
United States. President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
United States. Dept. of State. Bureau of Western Hemisphere Affairs
FA345
93 Document Box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 J.1
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for scholarly research. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into 6 subseries:
Subseries 1 - Politics, General, 1935-1970 Subseries 2 - National Political Campaigns, 1956-1968 Subseries 3 - New York State Gubernatorial Campaigns, 1958-1970 Subseries 4 - Polls, 1958-1970 Subseries 5 - Office of the Governor, 1958-1970 Subseries 6 - State Issues Files, 1973-1975
Scope and Contents note
This series contains a variety of material pertaining to Nelson Rockefeller's time as a politician, statesman, and public servant. The six subseries cover a broad spectrum of Rockefeller's involvement in political affairs, both on the state level and within the national arena. The majority of the series is concerned with Rockefeller's tenure as Governor of New York State, an office he held from 1959 to 1973. A range of public issues are represented in the series, primarily in the first subseries.
This series contains the office files of several members of Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. They document official activities in the execution of their duties as members of Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller which were never shown to him.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
International relations -- United States; Latin America; International economic relations; International relations; Public health -- Latin America; Social problems -- Latin America; State governments -- United States; United States; Venezuela; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Philanthropy -- United States; Philanthropy; Economics; Economic policy; Developing countries; Civics; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); New York (State); New York (N.Y.); National security -- United States; Education; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Federal government -- United States; Education -- Latin America; Government policy; Government agencies; Art, Primitive; Arts; Agriculture; Agriculture -- Latin America; Business enterprises, Foreign; Civic improvement; Brazil; Business; Museum of Primitive Art (New York, N.Y.); United Nations; United States. International Development Advisory Board; Rockefeller family; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); Inter-American Development Commission; Ruebhausen, Oscar M.; Rockefeller, Mary (Mary Todhunter Clark); Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich; Whitman, Ann; Morrow, Hugh; United States. Office of Inter-American Affairs; International Basic Economy Corporation; Hinman, George; United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services; United States. Dept. of State; United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; American International Association for Economic and Social Development; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); United States. President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); United States. Dept. of State. Bureau of Western Hemisphere Affairs
- Politics, General, 1935-1970; 1; 9 Document Box(es)
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1 is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries illustrates the evolution of Nelson Rockefeller as a political force both in New York state politics and on the national scene. Many of the early memoranda to Rockefeller are from Francis Jamieson, a Pulitzer Prize-winning newspaper journalist who had been hired by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., to head the public relations department in the Rockefeller Family Office. Jamieson gave political advice to Rockefeller early in his career. Nelson Rockefeller maintained a gubernatorial office in New York City, located at 22 West 55th Street, for much of his tenure as governor.
  - Affiliated Young Democrats, Inc., 1944-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence with the Democratic party organization; requests for interviews with NAR, declined.
  - Bloom, Sol, 1941-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between NAR and the Congressman from NY.
  - Borella, Victor, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Reports on labor attitudes during the campaign.
  - California, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    U.S. Senator Knowland's campaign, request for contribution; Crispus A. Wright for Congress Committee, request for contribution.
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Accounting, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Contributions, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Form Letters, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Invitations to Serve, Acceptances, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Invitations to Serve, Regrets, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Lists to Serve, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Promotion & Publicity, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Citizens Committee for the Reelection of Senator Irving Ives - Report, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Citizens for Christenberry (NYC Mayor), 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    NAR accepts invitation to become co-chairman of campaign.
  - Contributions, 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Political contributions made by NAR.
  - Contributions, 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Contributions, 1934-1944 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Contributions, Rockefeller Family (CLOSED FOLDER), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
  - Correspondence, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    NAR correspondence on political issues of interest.
  - Correspondence, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1969 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dart, Justin, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Correspondence re Dart's Organization Plan; binder of Dart's "Organization Plan for the Preservation of Personal Freedom & Free Enterprise."
  - Democratic Party, Correspondence, 1948-1957 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Invitations for NAR to attend functions; request for financial support of candidates, most declined.
  - Dewey, Thomas E., 1938-1956 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Correspondence between NAR and NYS Governor, invitations to inaugurals, discussions of NYS political issues.
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Eisenhower Economic Program (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, NAR Notes on speeches, campaign; clippings (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Policy Statement Summaries (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Speech Material (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Speech Material (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Speech Material (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - 1952 Campaign, Vandenberg Memo (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Memo from NAR on suggested Dwight D. Eisenhower positions on economic and social issues. Suggests names of individuals to help draft position papers.
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Anthology, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    A collection of Dwight D. Eisenhower statements to show his philosophy, prepared by Frank A. Jamieson; notes on work, copy of anthology.
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Anthology, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Anthology, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    Correspondence between NAR and Dwight D. Eisenhower on a wide range of political issues and discussions on public service.
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Correspondence, 1952-1968 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - General, 1952-1956 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Inauguration, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Inauguration, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - Invitations to NAR, 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - National Citizens for Eisenhower Congressional Committee, 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - New York State Citizens for Eisenhower, 1952-1956 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David - White House Meeting, March 20, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    Placards and photo of National Security Agency meeting.
  - Eisenhower, Milton & John S. D., 1959-1969 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    Correspondence with Milton and John Eisenhower, brother and son of the President.
  - Executive Branch Liaison Office, 1953-1955 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    Booklet with facts and quotes re Eisenhower administration, includes achievements.
  - Fair Campaign Practices Committee, 1954-1969 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    Notices of meetings; requests for donations.
  - Hall, Leonard, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    Correspondence and memoranda on Hall, who sought the gubernatorial nomination for governor in 1958.
  - Javits, Jacob J., 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Correspondence from NAR requesting support for Javits for Senator.
  - Lankler, Alexander, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    Aided in New Hampshire Presidential Primary campaign.
  - National Committee for an Effective Congress, 1952-1964 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    Organization that sought to defeat U.S. Senators they felt were ineffective in coping with world problems, involvement declined by NAR.
  - New York City - 9th (NYS) Assembly District, 1957-1964 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    Request for NAR contribution; "Legislative Report" for 9th District.
  - New York City - 4th (NYS) Assembly District, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    Correspondence with Eisenhower Republican Club.
  - New York City - 19th (U.S.) Congressional District, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    Richard Aldrich, candidate for U.S. Congress seeks NAR support.
  - New York City - 21st (NYC) Councilmanic District, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    Campaign leaflets & requests for NAR support for Citizens for Richard A. Hildebrand.
  - New York City - General, 1950-1964 (Box 7, Folder 59)
    Invitations to NAR to attend political dinners & receptions; requests for contributions & political recommendations.
  - New York City - Mayoralty Campaign Material, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    Miscellaneous memos.
  - New York City - Metropolitan Republican Club, 1957-1968 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    Statement of club re NAR for Governor, 1/20/58; clippings & correspondence regarding Draft Rockefeller for Governor; 3/21/58, John A. Roosevelt's appeal for right to form new Republican club.
  - New York City - National Republican Club, Inc., 1935-1966 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    Statements of dues paid 1963-1966; NAR appearance at Lincoln Day Dinner, 1951, 1958; letter of appreciation for NAR contribution, 1935.
  - New York City - Republican County Committee of the County of the New York, 1947-1958 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    Invitations to NAR for receptions & dinners; requests for contributions.